Jerome Blum
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Jerome Blum papers
1915-circa 1969 (bulk 1919-1935)
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Jerome Blum
2.6 linear feet
The papers of Jerome Blum measure 2.6 linear feet and are dated 1915-circa 1969 (bulk 1919-1935). Biographical material, correspondence, writings and notes, printed material, artwork, and photographs document the painter??s personal and professional life, and extensive travels.
Provenance
Most of the Jerome Blum papers were donated and loaned between 1965 and 1966 by Blum's widow, Frances Blum. Additional papers received in separate accessions were donated between 1965 and 1966 and microfilmed. A typescript copy of the final version of Life Answered was received in 1969.
Separated Material
Portions of the collection were loaned for microfilming and subsequently returned to the donor, including typescripts of Sherwood Anderson's letters, most of Blum's Theodore Dreiser material and other writings, and scrapbooks. Although this material is not technically part of the collection housed in AAA, copies are available on microfilm reels D237 and D238.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment.
Alternative Forms Available
Portions of the collection are available on 35mm microfilm reels D237-D238, and 2010 at Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of the collection as described in this finding aid does not reflect the order of the collection on microfilm.
Biographical Note
Jerome Blum (1884-1956) was a world traveler who found artistic inspiration while living in France and traveling to the American west, Hawaii, Japan, China, Cuba, and the South Seas (including a 10 month stay in Tahiti). Blum painted landscapes and seascapes of Southern France, and the many places he visited, as well as still lifes of exotic plants and fruits. He was living in Paris at the height of the Fauve movement and incorporated some of its ideas into his work, first inserting bold colors into his fairly conservative Post-Impressionist style. Later, he used significantly more saturated color, intense light, and bold forms.
Blum studied at the Francis J. Smith Art Academy in his native Chicago, and the Art Institute of Chicago. He went to Paris in 1906 with Lucile Swan, a sculptor and fellow student who eventually became his wife. There, he enrolled in the Ecole des Beaux-Arts for a brief period, studying with Luc Olivier Merson. Blum remained in Paris until 1910, participated in the 1909 and 1910 Salons d'Automne and received exhibition offers from Galerie Sagot, Paris, and Anderson Galleries, New York. While in France, Blum knew expatriates Jo Davidson, Arthur Dove, Samuel Halpert, Alfred Maurer, and John Marin. Halpert became a mentor of sorts, instructing him in painting Post-Impressionist landscapes, to which Blum soon added Fauvist color.
Once back in Chicago, Blum developed close friendships with writers Sherwood Anderson, Theodore Dreiser, and Ben Hecht that lasted for decades. His one-man show at Thurber's Art Gallery in 1911 received very mixed reviews ?? most likely it was the first time the Fauve palette was seen by Chicagoans, and most thought it too radical. When the mayor purchased a Blum painting from a 1912 Art Institute of Chicago group exhibition, the proceeds enabled Blum to visit the American west. Later that year, Blum and Lucile Swan traveled in Europe. They were married in Paris and took an extended honeymoon, continuing to travel in France until fall of the following year.
For a period of approximately 20 years, he exhibited extensively and enjoyed critical acclaim. During his many years of foreign residence, Blum returned to the United States periodically for exhibitions and family visits. He participated in a large number of solo exhibitions and group shows in the United States and France, including: Art Institute of Chicago, Arts Club of Chicago, O'Brien Galleries, and Albert Roullier Art Galleries in Chicago; Ainslie Galleries, Brooklyn Museum, Delphic Studios, Katz Gallery, M. Knoedler and Co., Whitney Museum of American Art, and Whitney Studio Club in New York; Boston Arts Club; Galerie de la Renaissance, Paris; Montlcair Art Museum, New Jersey; Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, Philadelphia; Worcester Art Museum, Massachusetts. Blum is represented in the permanent collections of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, the Smithsonian Institution, and the Whitney Museum of American Art.
Blum returned to New York in 1924 and Lucile filed for divorce. An auction of his work was held at the Anderson Galleries that year; Augustus John, George Biddle, Chester Dale, M. Knoedler, Kraushaar Galleries, and Jo Davidson were among the successful bidders.
In 1925, he married Frances Baum, a psychiatric social worker. They settled in Dampierre, France for eight years, and during this period traveled extensively throughout the country. Always an unconventional and fiercely independent person, Blum's mental health was fragile and deteriorated markedly in the early 1930s, during which time his painting output decreased dramatically. They Blums spent part of 1934 at the MacDowell Colony, Petersborough, New Hampshire. Once his fellowship was over, they moved to Key West, Florida, where Blum became increasingly disturbed.
Blum was admitted to the Bloomingdale Hospital, a private psychiatric institution in White Plains, New York, in 1935. But after being diagnosed a "hopeless case," he was transferred to a state hospital. While hospitalized, Blum continued writing copious notes and made many appeals for release. He died at the Hudson River State Hospital, Poughkeepsie, New York, in 1956.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Jerome Blum measure 2.6 linear feet and are dated 1915-circa 1969 (bulk 1919-1935). Biographical material, correspondence, writings and notes, printed material, artwork, and photographs document the painter's personal and professional life, and extensive travels.
Correspondence with friends, relatives, colleagues, publishers, galleries, museums, and collectors documents Blum's personal and professional life. An annotated list of important correspondents was supplied by his widow.
Blum was an avid writer. He published several short stories, and recorded reminiscences, thoughts, and daily events in a series of notebooks. These notes were the basis for Life Answered, an unpublished autobiography (eventually, edited and completed by Frances Blum). Also included are extensive notes and writings on a variety of subjects, including his extensive travels to Tahiti. Writings by other authors consist of "critical statements about Jerome Blum" and some of Frances Blum's writings on Theodore Dreiser.
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following index terms. People, families and organizations are listed under "Subjects" when they are the topic of collection contents and under "Names" when they are creators or contributors.
Subjects-Topical:
Painting, Modern -- 20th century -- New York (State) -- New York
Types of Materials:
Photographs; Works of art
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 6 series. Correspondence consists of two portions, one arranged alphabetically and the other chronologically. Writings of Jerome Blum are alphabetized by title; those by others are arranged by author. Biographical Material and Printed Material are arranged alphabetically by folder title. Photographs are categorized by subject: artwork, people, and places.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1915-1933 (Box 1; Reel 2010; 4 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1915-1966, undated (Box 1; Reels D237, 2010; 0.4 linear ft.)
Series 3: Writings, 1915-circa 1969, undated (Boxes 1-2; Reels D237, D238; 1.6 linear ft.)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1916-1965, undated (Box 3; Reels D237, 2010; 0.4 linear ft.)
Series 5: Artwork, 1930, undated (Box 4; Reel 2010; 2 folders)
Series 6: Photographs, undated (Box 4; Reels D238, 2010; 0.1 linear ft.)
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1915-1933, Series 1:
  This series consists of a publisher agreement, Jerome Blum and Lucile Swan's marriage certificate, passports and the transcript of a radio broadcast of Thomas L. Stix of "America's Grub Street Speaks" interviewing Jerome Blum on the subject of "Art and the Weather."
  - Agreement with Jonathan Cape and Harrison Smith, Inc., Publishers, 1929 (Box 1, Reel unfilmed)
  - Marriage Certificate of Jerome Blum and Lucile Swan, 1919, (frames 820-821) (Box 1, Reel 2010)
  - Passports, 1915-1920, (frames 822-825; 1920 passport unfilmed) (Box 1, Reel 2010)
  - Transcript of Radio Broadcast, 1933, (frames 807-817) (Box 1, Reel 2010)
- Correspondence, 1915-1966, undated, Series 2:; (Box 1; Reels D237, 2010; 0.4 linear ft.)
  Correspondence with friends, relatives, colleagues, publishers, galleries, museums, and collectors documents Blum's personal and professional life. Noted correspondents include Sherwood Anderson, George Biddle, Kay Boyle, William Bullitt, Mary and Padraic Colum, Theodore Dreiser, Guy Pene Dubois, Max Eastman, John Duncan Ferguson, Buckminster Fuller, Emma Goldman, Frank Harris, Hapgood Hutchinson, Elizabeth Sparhawk-Jones, Rockwell Kent, Alfred Kreymborg, Allan Ross MacDougall,Waldo Peirce, Llewylyn Powys, George Seldes, Doris Stevens, Art Young, and Ossip Zadkine. An annotated list including many of these correspondents, with notes on their occupations and their relationship to the Blums, was supplied by Frances Blum and can be found at the beginning of this series.
  Correspondence was received and microfilmed in two batches: the first is in alphabetical order, and the second is arranged chronologically.
  - Annotated List with Notes on Correspondents Supplied by Frances Blum, undated, (frames 5-7) (Box 1, Reel 2010)
  - Adams, "Frankie," circa 1930s, (frames 90-91) (Box 1, Reel D237)
  - Anderson, Sherwood and Eleanor, 1921-1933, undated, (D237 frames 53-89; 2010 frames 8-89, 92-96, 112) (Box 1, Reel D237/2010)
  - Armstrong, F. S. ?? Biddle, George and Helene, 1933-1938, undated, (frames 97-98, 194-211) (Box 1, Reel 2010)
  - Blum, Frances, 1925-1926, undated, (D238 frames 139-180; 2010 frames 103-138; 2 folders) (Box 1, Reel D238/2010)
  - Blum, Lucile, 1920-1921, undated, (frames 139-193) (Box 1, Reel 2010)
  - Boyle, Kay ?? Dos Passos, John, 1928-1940, undated, (frames 213-261) (Box 1, Reel 2010)
  - Dreiser, Theodore and Helen, 1936-1938, (frames 302-334) (Box 1, Reel 2010)
  - Drucker, Becky ?? Luhan, Mabel [Dodge], 1920-1956, undated, (frames 262-301, 335-445) (Box 1, Reel 2010)
  - McDougall, Allan Ross ("Dougie"), 1935-1955, undated, (frames 446-507) (Box 1, Reel 2010)
  - Marautaaroa (Queen of Tahiti) ?? Peirce, Waldo, 1915-1936, undated, (frames 508-552, 555-556) (Box 1, Reel 2010)
  - Powys, Llewelyn (with request from widow to borrow letters for publication), 1922-1940 (Box 1, Reel unfilmed)
  - Proetzel, Bobbie ?? Seabrook, William, 1927-1928, undated, (frames 553-554, 557-560) (Box 1, Reel 2010)
  - Seldes, George and Helen ?? Stevens, Doris, 1927-1939, undated, (frames 563-611) (Box 1, Reel 2010)
  - Stieglitz, Hannah (Mrs. Albert) ?? Zadkine, Ossip, 1915-1963, undated, (frames 561-562, 612-673) (Box 1, Reel 2010)
  - Correspondence, Miscellaneous and Unidentified, 1922- 1963, undated, (frames 677-759) (Box 1, Reel 2010)
  - Correspondence, 1917-1941, 1951-1966, undated, (frames 2-52, 178-298; 1965 unfilmed; 4 folders) (Box 1, Reel D237)
  - Obituaries and Condolence Letters upon the Death of Jerome Blum, 1956, (frames 299-379) (Box 1, Reel D237)
- Writings, 1915-circa 1969, undated, Series 3:; (Boxes 1-2; Reels D237, D238; 1.6 linear ft.)
  This series includes notebooks which Blum used to record his daily thoughts and activities, and on which he based his unpublished autobiography Life Answered. Frances Blum relied heavily on the notebooks to expand the manuscript, eventually completing it in circa 1969.
  Some writings by Blum, including material on China and Theodore Dreiser, Blum's draft of Life Answered, and drafts of portions of Life Answered - "Father and Mother," "Journal of the Last 20 Years," "Lucile" and "Marriage and Divorce" - were loaned to AAA for microfilming and were subsequently returned to the donor. These are available on 35 mm microfilm reels D237 and D238.
  This series is arranged as 2 subseries:
  3.1: Writings by Jerome Blum, 1915-circa 1969, undated
  3.2: Writings by Other Authors, 1921-1950, undated
  - Writings by Jerome Blum, 3.1:
    - "At Sea," undated (Box 1, Reel unfilmed)
    - "Chicago Sunday Afternoon," undated (Box 1, Reel unfilmed)
    - "Dark Virgin" (see: "Resurrection") (Box 1, Reel unfilmed)
    - "The Fox-Spirit," undated (Box 1, Reel unfilmed)
    - Life Answered (unpublished autobiography; see also: Notebooks) (Box 1, Reel unfilmed)
      - Notes ?? "Narrative ?? life?little pieces of narrative to be worked into book," undated (Box 1, Reel unfilmed)
      - Drafts, Deleted Portions, and Fragments, undated, (5 folders) (Box 1, Reel unfilmed)
      - Manuscript by Jerome and Frances E. Blum (copyrighted 1967 by Frances E. Blum), circa 1969, (3 folders) (Box 1, Reel unfilmed)
    - Lists, 1915, undated, (frames 837-842, and unfilmed) (Box 1, Reel D237)
    - Notebooks (source material for Life Answered), 1919-1942, (15 volumes in 4 folders) (Box 1, Reel unfilmed)
    - Notebooks (source material for Life Answered), undated, (26 volumes in 5 folders) (Box 2, Reel unfilmed)
    - Notes and Fragments, undated, (15 folders) (Box 2, Reel unfilmed)
    - Notes and Writings, undated (Box 2, Reel unfilmed)
    - "Resurrection" (also titled "Dark Virgin"; with untitled draft), undated (Box 2, Reel unfilmed)
    - Tahiti, 1920, undated, (D237 frames 1753-1898; D238, frames 1-57, and not microfilmed; 2 folders) (Box 2, Reel D237/D238)
    - Tahiti Material (clippings, rubbings, sketches), circa 1920-1952, undated, (frames 58-68) (Box 2, Reel D238)
    - Telephone Numbers, undated (Box 2, Reel unfilmed)
    - "To an Image of a Black Goddess from the Ivory Coast," undated (Box 2, Reel unfilmed)
  - Writings by Other Authors, 1921-1950, undated, 3.2:
    - Blum, Frances, "Theodore Dreiser," undated (Box 2, Reel unfilmed)
    - "Critical Statements about Jerome Blum," 1921-1950, undated, (frames 439-466) (Box 2, Reel D237)
- Printed Material, 1916-1965, undated, Series 4:; (Box 3; Reels D237, 2010; 0.4 linear ft.)
  This series includes articles, a book, clippings, catalogs and press releases. Clippings include obituaries of friends, book reviews, and articles about general art topics and world events. Many of the articles about, or mentioning, Blum contain reproductions of his work. Miscellaneous items include Key West, A Free Port: Survey and Report, a concert program, Town Hall, New York City and a map of Ulster County, New York.
  - Article - "Nobody's Home" by Sherwood Anderson, undated, (frames 827-831) (Box 3 (hol), Reel 2010)
  - Book - The Verdict of Bridlegoose by Llewelyn Powys [mentions Blum] with Obituary of the Author, 1926-1939 (Box 3 (hol), Reel unfilmed)
  - Clippings, 1916-1962, undated, (frames 380-438, and unfilmed; 2 folders) (Box 3 (hol), Reel D237)
  - Catalogs and Press Releases (Box 3 (hol), Reel D237/2010)
    - Jerome Blum Exhibitions, circa 1918-1965, undated, (D237 frames 639-836; 2010 frames 794-806, and unfilmed; 3 folders) (Box 3 (hol), Reel D237/2010)
    - Harry Shokler Exhibition (foreword by Blum), 1928 (Box 3 (hol), Reel unfilmed)
  - Clippings, undated, (frames 380-438, and unfilmed; 2 folders) (Box 3 (hol), Reel D237)
  - Miscellaneous Items, 1934-1961, undated (Box 3 (hol), Reel unfilmed)
  - This Quarter (vol. 2, no. 1 and vol. 3, no. 2; with stories by Blum), 1929-1930 (Box 3 (hol), Reel unfilmed)
- Artwork, 1930, undated, Series 5:; (Box 4; Reel 2010; 2 folders)
  Artwork by Blum consists of 10 pencil sketches. Artwork by others consists of 2 prints by Warton Esherick, inscribed to Blum, and 2 samples of Chinese calligraphy.
  - Artwork by Blum, undated, (frames 777-791) (Box 4 (pam), Reel 2010)
  - Artwork by Others, 1930, undated, (frames 777-791) (Box 4 (pam), Reel 2010)
- Photographs, undated, Series 6:; (Box 4; Reels D238, 2010; 0.1 linear ft.)
  - Artwork by Blum, undated, (D238 frames 74-1328; 2010 frames 768-774, and unfilmed; 3 folders) (Box 4 (pam), Reel D238/2010)
  - People: Jerome and Frances Blum; Jerome Blum, undated, (frames 64-73) (Box 4 (pam), Reel D238)
  - People: Unidentified, undated, (frames 764, 766-767) (Box 4 (pam), Reel 2010)
  - Places: Unidentified House and Well, undated (Box 4 (pam), Reel unfilmed)